You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we discover the
health benefits of sleep.
And we start with the connection
between the lack of sleep and weight gain.
Population studies have
found short sleep duration
has been associated with obesity
in both children and adults.
Observational studies can never
prove cause-and-effect, though.
Maybe the obesity is
leading to sleep loss
instead of the
other way around.
Obesity can cause arthritis,
acid reflux, and apnea,
all of which can
interfere with sleep.
The relationship between
obesity and sleep apnea,
where your breathing
repeatedly stops and starts
throughout the night, may
be explained by increased
tongue fat—fat deposited
inside the base of the tongue—
that may contribute to
obstructing your airway
when you sleep on your back.
The reverse causation
explanation of the link between
obesity and inadequate sleep
is bolstered by the finding
that weight loss interventions
can improve daytime sleepiness.
Potential confounding
factors also abound.
For example, people with
lower socioeconomic status
often work less desirable hours
such as rotating or overnight shifts,
or may live in
noisier neighborhoods
with poorer air
quality, more crime.
The link between inadequate
sleep and obesity persists
after controlling for
these kinds of factors,
but you can’t control
for everything.
You can’t know for sure if sleep
deprivation leads to weight gain
until you,...put it to the test.
Have people pull an all-nighter
and they get hungrier
and choose larger portions.
Randomize people to shave even just
a few hours of sleep off every night
and they start eating an average
of 677 calories more a day
compared to the normal
sleep control group.
Although individual
responses vary widely,
anywhere from eating 813
calories less per day
to as many as 1,437 calories more,
on average, studies found sleep
deprivation led people to overeat
by about 180 to
560 calories a day.
Restrict people’s sleep and they also
start craving unhealthier choices–
more snacks, more foods
that are fatty and sugary.
Stick people in a brain scanner
after staying awake all night,
or after few nights of four-hour
sleep, and their reward pathways
light up brighter in response
to high calorie foods.
Sleep deprivation bumps the
levels of the chief endocannabinoid
in the body, the natural chemical
we synthesize that binds
to the same receptors as the
active ingredient in marijuana.
This may help explain
the nighttime nibbling.
On the calories outside of the
equation, some short sleepers
may take the extra time to exercise;
others will be so sleepy
they exercise less.
The extra wakefulness may
raise calorie expenditure
up to about 100 calories a day,
but if sleep-deprived individuals
are overeating hundreds
of calories, over time
sleep deprivation may end up
putting the “wide” in wide awake.
With insufficient sleep
inadvertently leading to such
higher calorie intake, it’s no
surprise that 4 out of 5 studies
involving as few as 2–5
nights of sleep restriction
found an increase in body weight.
In other words, if you sleep
less, you may gain more
OK, but here’s where it gets crazy.
Even if you control calorie
intake, you still lose more fat
when you get more sleep.
Overweight subjects who
normally got between
6.5 to 8.5 hours of sleep a night
were randomized to two weeks
of either 8.5 hours of sleep
a night or 5.5 hours of sleep
on the same calorie-
controlled diet.
Then the groups switched
and spent another two weeks
on the opposite regimen.
So they spent a month living in
the lab so their diets and sleep
could be totally
controlled and monitored.
Just looking at the scales, sleep
duration didn’t seem to matter,
during both periods they ate
the same number of calories
and lost the same
amount of weight,
but most of the weight lost
while getting 8.5 hours was fat,
whereas most of the weight lost
when only getting 5.5 hours
of sleep a night
was lean body mass.
Same diet, but with more sleep
they ended up losing more than
twice as much body fat.
So you snooze you lose… fat!
In our next story,
we discover how getting just
one more hour of sleep a night
may help with weight control.
I featured a study
that found that
curtailing sleep can cut your
rate of body fat loss in half,
while exacerbating the
loss of lean mass.
To get better insight into what was
going on, researchers took fat
and muscle biopsies from people
after a night of sleep loss.
In terms of genes that
were turned on and off,
molecular signatures
were discovered suggesting
muscle breakdown
and fat buildup.
That was after an
all-nighter, though,
and in the weight-loss study
the sleep-restricted groups
ended up getting little
more than 5 hours a night.
What about a more realistic
scenario like sleeping
just like one hour
less a night?
Overweight adults were
randomized to 8 weeks
of a calorie restricted
diet or the same diet
combined with just 5 days a week
of one hour a night less sleep.
The sleep restricted group achieved
the one hour a day less sleep
on weekdays but ended up sleeping
an hour more on the weekend days.
So overall, they just cut about
3 hours of sleep out of their week.
Would just those few hours a week
make any weight loss difference?
On the scale, no, but in
the normal sleep group,
80% of the weight loss was fat,
whereas in the group just
missing a few hours of sleep a week
it was the opposite—
80% of the loss was lean.
This shows that a few hours of
“catch up sleep” on the weekends
is insufficient, and may in fact
be contributing to the problem
based on “social jetlag” effect
I explored in a previous video.
A comparable study
was designed for kids,
but the sleeping periods
only lasted a week.
Eight- to eleven-year olds
were randomized to either
increase or decrease their time
in bed by 1.5 hours per night
for a week and then
switch the following week.
They ate an average of 134 calories
more on the days they slept less
and gained in that
week about half a pound
compared to the sleep-more week.
The question then becomes would
sleeping more facilitate weight loss?
When it comes to body fat,
can we just, sleep it off?
The benefit of interventional
studies is that you can demonstrate
cause and effect, but
observational studies can allow you
to more easily track
people and their behaviors
over a longer time span.
For example, researchers
followed a group of
mostly overweight individuals
who started out to averaging
less than six hours of sleep
a night for more than five years.
During that time, about
half maintained that schedule
but the other half increased
their sleep duration up to
seven or eight hours a night and
ended up gaining 5 pounds less fat.
A study entitled “Sleeping habits
predict the magnitude of fat loss”
(among those cutting calories)
found that every
extra hour of sleep
at night was associated with
an extra 1-and-a-half pounds
of weight loss over a period
of about 3 to 6 months.
That’s not the same as randomizing
people to extra sleep, though.
Maybe they were sleeping more
because they were exercising more
and that’s the real reason
they lost more weight?
Getting people to bump their
sleep from about 5.5 hours up to 7
can lead to an overall decrease
in appetite within two weeks,
particularly for sugary
and salty foods.
A four-week study getting
habitually short sleepers to sleep
about an extra hour a night
led them to consume about
two fewer spoonful’s worth
of sugar a day compared to
the control group but
this didn’t translate
into any changes in
body composition.
A twelve-week study,
on the other hand,
randomizing overweight
and obese individuals
to a weight loss intervention
with or without a sleep component
found that the sleep group lost
weight significantly faster.
A national cross-sectional
survey suggested lower obesity rates
among kids in households that
regularly ate dinner together
as a family, got adequate
sleep, and limited screen times,
and so Harvard researchers
decided to try to...
put those behaviors
to the test.
A six-month randomized trial
to improve household routines
for obesity prevention among young
children resulted in a lower BMI.
Normally it’s hard to
tease out the effects
of multi-component
interventions, but in this case
exhortations to limit overall
TV watching didn’t work,
and the families were already
eating together 6 days a week
and so that didn’t
change much either.
The only thing they
were able to get the kids
to significantly alter
was their sleep,
and so the improved weight
outcomes may be attributed
at least in part to the ¾ hour
average increase in nightly sleep.
Overall, most sleep
improvement interventions
tended to show
improved weight loss.
I was intrigued to look up
the one study that didn’t.
The nice thing about
systematic reviews
(as opposed to so-called
“narrative” reviews)
is that they exhaustively
include mention of every study
that meets some
prespecified criteria.
This keeps reviewers
from cherry-picking,
but it can also lead to the
inclusion of some strange studies.
In this case, a randomized controlled
trial of didgeridoo playing,
the indigenous Australian
wind instrument.
Those randomized to the didgeridoo
to improve their sleep quality
did not lose any weight,
but they also failed to improve
the quality of their sleep
(or, likely, that
of their neighbors).
Did you know that lactucin,
the hypnotic component of lettuce,
is a natural dietary
remedy for insomnia?
Here’s the story.
There is a perception that time
spent asleep is time wasted,
but it is widely recognized that
inadequate sleep is associated
with multiple acute
and chronic conditions,
and results in the increased
risk of death and disease.
Force people to go one week with
only six hours of sleep a night,
and you can change expression
of more than 700 genes.
The most dire effect may
be endothelial dysfunction.
The endothelium is the thin layer of
cells that covers the internal surface
of blood vessels and is responsible
for allowing our arteries
to relax and dilate
back open properly.
Randomize people for about a week
to get five rather than seven hours
of sleep, and just that two-hour
difference a night resulted
in a significant impairment
in artery function.
Okay, but what do these numbers mean?
How bad is a week of 5-hour nights?
Sleep deprivation is no joke.
The magnitude of impairment is similar
to that reported in people who smoke,
have diabetes, or have
coronary artery disease.
No wonder people who sleep less than
seven hours a night may experience
a 12% to 35% increased
risk of premature death
compared to those who
get a full seven hours.
Yet a significant proportion
of the population may
routinely get less than that.
Sufficiently long, restful
sleep sessions each night
are said to be an indisputable
cornerstone of good health.
Okay, so what can we do about it?
Those who have sleep apnea,
a common consequence of obesity
that interferes with sleep, benefit
from the use of CPAP machines
while they're losing the weight to treat
the underlying cause, hopefully.
But what if apnea isn't your problem?
What if you just have trouble
falling asleep or staying asleep?
In my book How Not to Diet, I have a
whole section on sleep enhancement,
where I go through the Four
Rules of Sleep Conditioning
and the Four Rules
of Sleep Hygiene.
What if you follow those guidelines
but still can't get to sleep?
Any natural dietary remedies?
I already have videos on using
kiwifruit to fight insomnia,
and tart cherries, too.
Are there any vegetables
that might help?
Lactuca sativa is a plant that
has been traditionally used
in the treatment of insomnia.
What is this exotic sounding
leafy vegetable? Lettuce!
Evidently lettuce extracts have been
used from the time of the Roman Empire
as agents with sedative and
sleep-inducing properties.
Lettuce actually does have a hypnotic
substance in it called lactucin,
which is what makes
lettuce taste a little bitter.
But you don't know if it actually
works until you put it to the test.
And it works...in toads.
But it also works in rodents.
Sleep in both mice and rats
is enhanced by romaine lettuce.
They used romaine since
it has a higher lactucin content
compared to other lettuces.
Okay, but does it work in people?
About 10 years ago, a study was
published in which insomnia sufferers
were randomized to receive lettuce seed
oil, oil extracted from lettuce seeds.
Within a week, about 70% of those
in the lettuce seed oil group
said their insomnia very much
or much improved,
compared to only 20% in
the placebo control group.
The researchers concluded that lettuce
seed oil was found to be a useful,
safe sleeping aid in geriatric patients
suffering from sleeping difficulties.
They chose to study older individuals
because insomnia affects surprisingly
20 to 40% of older adults
at least a few nights a month.
You think that's bad. Sleep
disturbances can plague as many
as nearly 8 out of 10 women
during pregnancy.
Of course, there's lots
of different sleeping pills,
but they may endanger
the fetus or mother.
For example, doctors frequently
prescribe Ambien for pregnant women
who have trouble sleeping, but Ambien
use is associated with a wide range
of adverse pregnancy outcomes
like low birth weight babies,
premature birth, and cesarean section.
And the use of valium during
pregnancy has been linked
to birth defects
including limb deficiencies.
There has to be a better way.
What about trying lettuce?
The lettuce oil study had
a number of limitations.
For example, it was only single-blind,
meaning the researchers knew
who was on the lettuce supplements
and who was on placebo,
which could have introduced some bias.
But the researchers essentially said,
"Give us a break. Big pharma
has billions to spend on research.
No one wants to fund
studies on lettuce."
Finally, we got a double-blind,
placebo-controlled study,
but this time on a whole food,
not just a lettuce seed extract.
Yeah, but how do you come
up with a placebo lettuce?
How are you going to hide who
gets lettuce and who doesn't?
Well, you can't fit a head
of lettuce into a capsule,
but you can fit whole lettuce seeds.
And here we go: a double-blind
randomized placebo-controlled trial
on lettuce seeds for
pregnancy-related insomnia.
A hundred pregnant women
with insomnia were randomized
to receive capsules containing
either a quarter teaspoon
of ground lettuce seeds or
a placebo for two weeks,
and those on the lettuce seeds
saw a significant improvement
in a sleep quality index score
compared to placebo
with no reported side effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.